Guide to the Federal Theatre Project personal papers, 1926-1989
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
- Federal Theatre Project personal papers, 1926-1991
  - Leve, Samuel, 1951 (Oversize 27)
    Set model for the play Dinosaur Wharf produced at the National Theatre in 1951. Set is made out of wood and paper, and measures 13 inches by 7 3/8 inches by 8 1/4 inches. The set consists of a wharf with a small building on the left hand side. In the background is a hand drawn cityscape. The model is encased in glass. A label on the model states: "'Dinosaur Wharf,' at the National Theatre. Presented by Terese Hayden. Written by Joel Wyman. Directed by Miss Hayden. Setting designed by Samuel Leve."
  - Levin, Bertha Greenberg, 1936; 1981 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Scrapbook containing Milwaukee newspaper clippings about the Federal Theatre Project. Most clippings are from May to October 1936.
  - Lewis, Elaine, 1931-1939 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Can You Hear Their Voices? By Hallie Flanagan and Margaret Ellen clifford for Vassar Experimental Theatre plays; Program for Can You Hear Their Voices?; encyclopedia entry on Federal Theatre; What was Federal Theatre? pamphlet by Hallie Flanagan.
  - Litvinoff, Valentina, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    2 Photocopies of images of dancers.
  - Longwood college, circa 1935-1939 (Oversize 9)
    Federal Theatre Project costume that includes a green velvet vest and pants.
  - Lovelace, 1930s (Oversize 23)
    Tomato marionette.
  - Mahlmann, Lewis, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Oakland Recreation Department marionette report (in scrapbook form) includes report, photographs, scripts.
  - Mahlmann, Lewis, circa 1935-1939 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Puppet teaching - all cloth puppets manual for the city of New York Education and Recreation Department.
  - Manisoff, Manuel, 1937-1939 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Newspaper clippings. Programs: Prelude to Swing, Spirochete, Unto Such Glory / Hymn to the Rising Sun.
  - Manisoff, Manuel, 1937-1939 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Photographs of the production Unto Such Glory; photograph of Blanding Sloan, George Gerwing, Hallie Flanagan, and Herbert Humphreys at the first Sponsors' meeting in Philadelphia; photograph of crowd outside theatre in Philadelphia, cast of Spirochete; postcard from Katherine Cale.
  - Manisoff, Manuel, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Production bulletin for Philadelphia production of Spirochete includes set and costume design, newspaper clippings, programs.
  - Manisoff, Manuel, circa 1937 - 1939 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Federal Theatre magazine - First Federal Summer Theatre A Report; Two documents: General outline for statement of the plan; Planning committee on Field Problems, resolutions.
  - Marshall, E. G., October 3, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Photocopy of review of Big Blow from the New York Times.
  - McLean, Scott, 1926-1937 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Photocopies of programs from productions performed in Jacksonville, Florida: Carrier-Jamboree; Aida; Criminal at Large; A Doll's House; Dulcy; Escape; Fly Away Home; The Girl of the Golden West; Hay Fever and Anne Pedersdotter; Lightnin'; The Ninth Guest; One Sunday Afternoon; The Pizen Song; R-U-R; Remember the Day; The Rise of Silas Lapham; Saturday's children; She Stoops to conquer (original and photocopy); Smilin' Through; Twelfth Night; Ten Nights in a Barroom; Uncle Tom's Cabin (original).
  - McLean, Scott, 1936-1939 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Florida Federal Theatre report - Analysis of attendence records, with averages and recapitulations; Historical drama tour series outlines for class study - When Knighthood was in Flower; Time Magazine clipping; article - Our Theatre by Lerom, L. D.; typewritten copy of Movie stars plead for Jacksonville Federal Theatre article origanlly in the Jacksonvelle Journal; photocopies of newspaper articles.
  - McLean, Scott, circa 1936-1939 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Negatives and three slides. Copies of photographs of Federal Theatre productions in Jacksonville, Florida; slides of a drawing of the Florida Federal Theatre bus.
  - Medovoy, George, 1970s (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Photocopies. Correspondence between Medovoy and Federal Theatre employees; radio talk titled Yiddish Theatre in the california WPA; photographs of scenes and sets from Yiddish Federal Theatre productions.
  - Meredith, Betty, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    Photocopies of a review and publicity about the Federal Theatre in California, and the Experimental Theatre.
  - Mesa, Fernando, circa 1937-1938 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    Androcles and the Lion playscript.
  - Mesa, Fernando, January 14, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    The Dragon's Wishbone playscript.
  - Mesa, Fernando, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    Letter to Lorraine Brown and newspaper clippings.
  - Mesa, Fernando, 1936-1940 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    Loose materials removed from scrapbook pages. Includes: Newspaper clippings, programs, Federal Theatre project research on plays, memoranda and correspondence.
  - Mesa, Fernando, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    Sleeping Beauty playscript.
  - Mesa, Fernando, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs script, Syl file.
  - Mesa, Fernando, 1930s (Box 12, Folder 13)
    Syl (Art Director of the FTP) file on the play Coppelia, includes hand drawn set designs and typed production notes.
  - Mesa, Fernando, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    Syl (Art Director of the FTP) file includes memoranda, handwritten notes, set and stage designs.
  - Mesa, Fernando, 1936-1938 (Oversize 24)
    Scrapbook pages containing programs, newspaper clippings, telegrams, tickets, some Federal Theatre correspondence, and three pasted in artifacts - doll clothing created by the WPA Sewing colored Unit and a doll size artists palette. Much of the material is from the centro Asturiano Theatre, or relates to Tampa, Florida productions. Some Spanish language material.
  - Morcom, James, circa 1936-1939 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    Program and newspaper review for production of Jefferson Davis; Morcom identification work card.
  - Murray, Donald, 1936-1939 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    Photocopies of correspondence between Murray, Hallie Flanagan, and E. Woodward regarding J. Howard Miller.
  - Nadel, Sue Remos, 1936-1938 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    Photocopies of newspaper articles and programs about the WPA dance unit productions and strikes.
  - New York Public Library, December 8, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    Bassa Moona program, New York.
  - New York Public Library, June 30, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    The Bat program performed in Los Angeles.
  - New York Public Library, May 22, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    Two programs for Battle Hymn as produced in New York.
  - New York Public Library, March 2, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    Two programs for Big Blow performed in chicago.
  - New York Public Library, June 19, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    Candide program.
  - New York Public Library, March 4, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    Program and flyer for Chalk Dust performed in New York.
  - New York Public Library, May 15, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    Class of '29 program, New York production.
  - New York Public Library, January 8, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    Seven programs for Doctor Faustus performed in New York. One program contains an insert and an audience survey questionnaire.
  - New York Public Library, 1936-1939 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Gilbert & Sullivan Opera company program.
  - New York Public Library, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    Help Yourself, three programs from New York.
  - New York Public Library, September 26, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    Horse Eats Hat program from New York.
  - New York Public Library, July 8, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Laburnum Grove program from Hartford, connecticut production.
  - New York Public Library, April 10, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    The Mikado (swing version) two programs from New York city productions.
  - New York Public Library, March 1936 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Murder in the Cathedral program from New York production.
  - New York Public Library, May 23, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    One-Third of a Nation, two Living Newspaper programs for productions in Seattle, Washington.
  - New York Public Library, 1936-1939 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    Programs including the following productions: Haiti; How Long Brethren?; It Can't Happen Here; Life and Death of an American; Macbeth; The Mikado; The Path of Flowers; Pinocchio; Processional; Prologue to Glory; Unto Such Glory.
  - New York Public Library, March 17, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    Sing For Your Supper, five programs from New York productions.
  - New York Public Library, January-February 1939 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    The Theatre Abroad volume 1 number 4.
  - New York Public Library, March-April 1939 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    The Theatre Abroad volume 1 number 5.
  - New York Public Library, May 1939 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    The Theatre Abroad volume 1 number 6.
  - Norvelle, Lee, 1936 (Oversize 25)
    Scrapbook containing newspaper clippings, programs, and photographs of actors from Federal Theatre plays produced at B. F. Keith's theatre in Indianapolis.
    November 13, 1935 Dr. Lee Norvelle was appointed Director of the Indiana State Federal Theatre Project. He was granted a leave of absence from Indiana University, and moved to Indianapolis on November 18 to initiate the project. B. F. Keith's theatre was leased and served as the headquarters of the project for it's duration. The first production opened March 2, 1936. The last production closed in June 1937.
  - Page, Ruth, 1930s-1940s (Box 6, Folder 18)
    Photocopies of reviews of the production Frankie and Johnny.
  - Pierson, Mrs. Eily, circa 1936-1939 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    Macbeth program.
  - Popewell, Les, 1930s-1944 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    Federal Theatre programs: Hamlet, Chalk Dust, Rip Van Winkle, Spirochete, An Evening of Short Plays by Eugene O'Neill, The Lonely Man (with multiple signatures), Burning the Mortgage, The Good Old Summertime, Triple A Plowed Under; Newspaper clipping for "That's a Laff" (1944); entries on Federal Theatre plays from a book on Theatre.
  - Rabson, carolyn, circa 1935-1939 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Fool's Gold script.
  - Rabson, Carolyn, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Photocopies. From Ben Russak files - press release for Treasure Hunt (The Disappointment); notes and correspondence about the adaptation of The Disappointment.
  - Rather, Lois Foster, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Photocopies. Chart of San Francisco productions through June 9, 1937; organization chart; Toward a Living Theatre; first draft of Answers to Questions from Howard Miller. Foster identification cards and termination notice.
  - Rella, Ettore, circa 1930s (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Please communicate playscript.
  - Rhodes, Irwin, 1937-1938; 1976 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Corresondence between various Federal Theatre administrators; speech given by Rhodes on the Federal Theatre; blank personnel forms.
  - Rhodes, William / Rich, Shirley, circa 1936-1939 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Three pages of Hallie Flanagan notes; Programs for One-Third of a Nation, Doctor Faustus, Swing It, Pinocchio.
  - Rodericks, George, December 23, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Flat Lux playbill autographed by Rodericks.
  - San Francisco Archive for the Performing Arts, circa 1937 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Photocopies of programs for Battle Hymn, and A Touch of Brimstone.
  - Saul, Oscar, circa 1937 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    Revolt of the Beavers published script.
  - Saul, Oscar, 1939-1940 (Box 17)
    Green scrapbook with newspaper clippings covering productions of the play Medicine Show.
  - Savage, George, 1938-1939 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Promotional flier for Awake and Sing at Daly's Theatre; program for The Taming of the Shrew; flier for Summer Theatre in Seattle.
  - Savage, George, circa 1936-1939 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Newspaper clippings and five photographs depicting Savage, Mrs. James, J. Howard Miller and Guy Williams, Burton James, Federal Theatre theatre.
  - Schlossberg, Alan, 1938; 1989 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Newspaper clipping from 1989 about the Federal Theatre; Programs: Sunday Night Varieties; Pins and Needles; Here's Looking at You.
  - Schulman, Sol, July 24, 1936 and January 17, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Injunction Granted and One-Third of a Nation living newspaper programs.
  - Schulman, Sol, 1936-1939 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    Programs: The Cradle Will Rock; Pinocchio; Adelante; Battle Hymn; Big Blow; Class of '29; A Doris Humphrey-charles Weidman Dance Program; The Dance of Death; Doctor Faustus; The Mikado; Life and Death of an American; It Can't Happen Here; Haiti; How Long Brethern?; On the Rocks; Prologue to Glory; Processional; The Sun and I; Run Little chillun; Buffalo Historical Marionettes; Turpentine,
  - Shaw, John Bennett, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    Playbill and herald for the New York production of On The Rocks.
  - Shepherd, Louise, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    Souvenir program for The Lost colony.
  - Shibley, Eleanor, circa 1930s (Box 7, Folder 16)
    Four photographs of Eleanor Shibley in costume. These are not the original photographs.
  - Shohet, Max, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
    Paper on the Federal Theatre Project.
  - Shrewsbury, Robert, 1936-1939 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    Programs: Triple A Plowed Under; Power; 1935; If Ye Break Faith; Mississippi Rainbow; The Man in the Tree; High Tor; Faust; The Farmer Takes a Wife; An Enemy of the People; Outside Looking In; The Party is Over; Petrified Forest; Whom Dreams Possess.
  - Silvera, John D., April 26, 1938 and August 31, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    Correspondence from Silvera to Ben Russak concerning the Negro Theatre and Theodore Brown.
  - Sporn, Paul, 1937-1938 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    Photocopies of corresopndence and flyer regarding the Detrot Federal Theatre.
  - Stevens, Mark, June 14, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    A Nationwide Search for Early American Printing: A talk over station WDAF (Kansas city) by Douglas c. McMurtrie.
  - Tyler, Converse, 1937-1938 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    Newsclippings about the play "This Pretty World," program for a production of "And You, My Friend, Farewell."
  - Unknown donor, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    Awake and Sing, typed reviews and handwritten notes.
  - Unknown donor, circa 1936-1939 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    The Children of Salem marionette playscript.
  - Unknown donor, circa 1936-1939 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    Circus Days hand drawn set designs; marionette review.
  - Unknown donor, circa 1936-1939 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    The Disappointment playscript.
  - Unknown donor, circa 1936-1939 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Miscellaneous - flyers, contest announcements, weekly program schedules. Includes: color pamphlet for upcoming productions including Eugene O'Neill's Four One Act Plays of the Sea, Processional, A Hero is Born; Buffalo historical marionettes brochure; Beaver club letter; caravan herald; contest information; covers for weekly schedules, Daly's childrens' schedule; Drama week herald; Elliott's Repertory; Federal Theatre presents brochure; Living Theatre herald for talks; marionettes in the news; Marionette Theatre brochure; new summer session of the Negro Dramatists Lab herald.
  - Unknown donor, May 1936 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    The Poetic Theatre program,
  - Unknown donor, circa 1936-1939 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Tobias and the Angel program,
  - Unknown donor, circa 1936-1939 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    The Totem marionettes playscript.
  - Vaeth, Alice, April 15, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Photocopy of Joseph Lentz letter to Alice Vaeth,
  - Veenstra, John, August 1942 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Theatre Arts magazine: The Negro in the American Theatre.
  - Velonis, Anthony, January 1939 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    Brooklyn Museum print show. Printed booklet titled: Information for artists on the Brooklyn Museum Print Show.
  - Velonis, Anthony, circa 1936-1939 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    Native Ground painted promotional design, original artwork.
  - Velonis, Anthony, July-August 1938 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    Correspondence on the Federal Art Project and Velonis possible employment on a traveling art project.
  - Velonis, Anthony, circa 1936-1939 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    The Path of Flowers original artwork.
  - Velonis, Anthony, circa 1936-1939 (Oversize 22, Folder 3)
    R.U.R. original artwork for poster.
  - Velonis, Anthony, May 1947 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    Serigraph Quarterly volume II number 2.
  - Velonis, Anthony, circa 1936-1939 (Oversize 22, Folder 4)
    Sketches documenting silkscreening practices and tools.
  - Velonis, Anthony, circa 1936-1939 (Oversize 22, Folder 5)
    Pencil sketch titled "New Voices."
  - Velonis, Anthony, circa 1930s (Box 13, Folder 21)
    Technique, Art and Power, handwritten three page essay.
  - Velonis, Anthony, circa 1936-1939 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    What is a Silkscreen Print? five page typed essay.
  - Vondersmith, Elizabeth R., circa 1936-1939 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Photocopy of script for The Willow Plate - an original hand puppet play based on an old chinese legend.
  - Wagner, Irene, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Script for New Living Newspaper volume 1 number 2 by Irene Wagner with Barry Levy and Richard Vitere.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 24)
    American Jubilee sheet music.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 25)
    The Forgotten Music of Triple A Plowed Under (1936), Power (1937), and One Third of a Nation (1938) by Deborah Novak, thesis.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    Leaning on a Shovel sheet music.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, 1936-1937; 1967 (Box 13, Folder 27)
    Newsclippings; Living Newspaper programs.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, December 2, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 28)
    Orchestration for scenes from unnamed play. "ARR. G.A.E. 12/2/36" written on sheet music.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, circa 1936-1937 (Box 13, Folder 29)
    Orchestration for Power, sheet music and lyrics.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, circa 1936-1937 (Box 13, Folder 30)
    Power - TVA song, sheet music.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, 1936-1938 (Box 13, Folder 31)
    Power newspaper clippings, Processional program, Federal Music Program composers Forum Laboratory featuring Werner Josten program, small play production photograph.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 32)
    Power script with small scrap of sheet music.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, 1939 (Box 14, File 1)
    Sing For Your Supper, lyrics and sheet music for Opening Night.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    Sing For Your Supper, lyrics and sheet music for Perspiration.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    Sing For Your Supper, sheet music for Sixty Families.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    Sing For Your Supper, published sheet music for The Story of Horn.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    Sing For Your Supper playscript.
  - Wainer, Lee and Reta, May 9, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Wallace, Lea Samuels, 1937-1939 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Federal Theatre volume 2 number 4 with drawing on cover; Programs for Trojan Incident, Adelante, Ballet caravan; Four issues of Federal Theatre Project Dance Bulletin; Administrative memorandum on vacations; House of Representatives Bill H.R. 8239; Newspaper clippings.
  - Wasserman, Dale, circa 1936-1939 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Programs: Gods of the Lightning; Run, Little chillun; Days Without End.
  - Williams, Jay, January 1939 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    Jobless Blues lyrics and sheet music.
  - Zimmerman, Leland L., 1935-1936 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    Administrative correspondence; Instructions for Federal Theatre Projects; WPA supplement number 1 to bulletin 29; Washington Marionette Festival notice; Semi-monthly letter of the Federal Theatre Project.